<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The yeomans prerogative, or, The honour of husbandry. A sermon preached to some, and dedicated to all the yeomen and farmers of Kent. May 27. 1652. By Nathanael Newbury, master in arts, and minister of God's word at Ludenham, in the said county.</title>
            <author>Newbury, Nathanael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E684_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207053</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866129</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118393</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118393)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E684[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The yeomans prerogative, or, The honour of husbandry. A sermon preached to some, and dedicated to all the yeomen and farmers of Kent. May 27. 1652. By Nathanael Newbury, master in arts, and minister of God's word at Ludenham, in the said county.</title>
                  <author>Newbury, Nathanael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Moxon, for J.N.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLII [1652, i.e. 1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 6.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Agriculture --  England --  Weald of Kent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118393:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Yeomans Prerogative, OR, The HONOUR of HUSBANDRY.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached to ſome, and Dedicated to all the YEOMEN and FARMERS of KENT. <hi>May</hi> 27. 1652.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Newbury,</hi> Maſter in Arts, and Miniſter of God's Word at <hi>Ludenham,</hi> in the ſaid County.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Tim. 2.6.</bibl>
               <p>The Husbandman that laboureth, muſt be firſt partaker of the Fruits.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Moxon,</hi> for <hi>J. N.</hi> MDCLII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118393:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118393:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> The Yeomen and Farmers of <hi>Kent, Particularly,</hi> To my very Loving Neighbours,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Pordage,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Greenſtreet,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Platt,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſaac Terry,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stephen Barnes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Markes Cullen,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>And the reſt of the courteous Auditours of this SERMON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not ſo much to Vindicate the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of my intentions and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances (though too enviouſly or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably traduced by ſome) as it is to aſſert the eminency of my reſpects unto you, and all others of your Order; that I now preſent to your more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous review, what I lately preached, and you favourably heard, this <hi>Sermon:</hi> I never yet doted ſo much upon any of my Compoſures, as to think'em worthy by the midwifery of the preſs, to be delivered unto publike cenſure or protection. And for this, it might have been contented to have dyed amongſt its follows in my ſtudy, and layn there wrapt up in its own winding-ſheet; but that I held it improper to light a Candle, and then preſently put it under a Buſhel.</p>
            <p>I have ſeen and heard of Sermons, addreſſed and directed to the honour of other callings much inferior to yours; but if I miſtake not, I have the happineſs to be the firſt, who
<pb facs="tcp:118393:3"/>have thus publiquely remonſtrated their Miniſterial affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions unto Husbandry; a calling that (as I hope I have in ſome good degree made it appear) is as capable of our moſt induſtrious and honourable reſpects, as any other.</p>
            <p>It is the trivial excuſe of many writers, to pretend the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of friends, for the publiſhing their conceptions; and it is the ſlight policy of others, with a ſeeming modesty, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the weakneſs, worthleſneſs, or abortiveneſs of their labours: thereby indeed vehemently deſiring that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plavſe, which they would be thought to decline: I have no ſuch excuſe for this publication. I do clearly profeſs, that it was my ambition to promote the honour of your calling, and the ſalvation of your ſoules, which prevail'd with me to preach and to print this <hi>Sermon.</hi> Nor is ſuch ambition to be blamed, but cheriſhed; For as<note n="*" place="margin">S. W. D.</note> one has ſolidly and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutely obſerved, <hi>Ambition</hi> (if the vulgar acception of the word were corrected) would ſignifie no more, than an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary lifting of the feet in the rough wayes of honour; and hath a warmth (till it be chafed into a Fever) which is neceſſary for every virtuous breaſt. And the Apoſtle ſays plainly,<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>It is good to be zealouſly affected alwayes in a good thing:</hi> Ambire, ardenter ſectari, ſayes the Scholiast; Ambitiouſly, and ardently to purſue it. I have given you the reaſon of this dedication, my reſpect unto you; Ile now add the reaſon why I do ſo reſpect you.</p>
            <p>To you who heard this <hi>Sermon,</hi> and to whom it was more particularly deſigned, my reſpects are oblidgedly deep and many; I reſpect you as my very friendly Neighbours, as my very benevolent friends, and ſome of you as my Pariſhioners, the immediate and undenyable Objects of my Miniſterial care and affections; you are dear unto me in the Lord, it is the ſubſtance of all my ſtudies and contrivements, how I may advance your Spiritual good: Knowing therefore that encouragements unto well-doing, are the Noblest and moſt prevailing documents, I quickly reſolved upon this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; hoping it may prove the moſt compendious Method,
<pb facs="tcp:118393:3"/>both to encourage and inſtruct you, ſince hereby I have the advantage at once to demonſtrate both your dignity and your duty.</p>
            <p>Again, you reap unto me temporal things; and is it not my duty to ſow unto you ſpiritual? True it is, that we Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters do this, in the ordinary and perpetual ſeed-time of our weekly Sermons: And that we do ſo, we have nothing to glory of<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16.</note> for <hi>neceſſity is laid upon us yea, wo is unto us, if</hi> (ſo of't at leaſt) <hi>we preach not the Goſpel.</hi> But this I have done willingly, and not out of neceſſity, that you may have ſome teſtimony of my Gratitude, as well as of my duty.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, to you All, who in a Civill ſence are (and it is my ſerious ambition, that you may be in a religious ſenſe too)<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 6.13.</note> the pith and ſubſtance of the County, my reſpects are due for your Calling ſake. A Calling, ſo worthy the indiſpenſable reſpects of all men, that if I would in this Epiſtle permit my officious pen to expatiate, I ſhould ſooner want paper, then matter to dilate upon; but that were in part to prevent the buſineſs of the <hi>Sermon</hi> and to entertain you longer in the Porch, then I intend to do in the Houſe. In a word then, my opinion of your Calling is this: that I think the Sun, who is (under God) the univerſal Paerent of fruitfulneſs, is not more neceſſary or comfortable to the world, than is Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry.</p>
            <p>'Tis a Calling ſo venerable, that it has taught the moſt barbarous Nations, the moſt inſulting Conquerors, a ſaving ingenuity, and a merciful tenderneſs; <hi>Parce Agricolis,</hi> Have a care to preſerve the Husbandman, was the publike voice of Nature and Nations;<note n="*" place="margin">Diod Sicul. lib. 2. Bibl.</note> One of the moſt ancient Hiſtorians, relates it to have been the cuſtome of the Indians, that even in their mutual devaſtations, and invaſive wars, they on all ſides ſpared the Husbandman; as well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how advantageouſly uſefull he was to both parties. And <hi>Plutarch</hi> obſerves, that the old <hi>Corinthians</hi> and inhabitants of <hi>Megara,</hi> were ſo reſpectful to the Husbandman, that no man would by any means diſturb or endamage him, Another
<pb facs="tcp:118393:4"/>reports, that <hi>Cyrus</hi> commanded it to be proclaimed, That the Husbandman ſhould be permitted to follow his imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Xenephon de Cyri. Jnſtit lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and preſerved unharmed. And <hi>Suidas</hi> gives this full alteſtation to <hi>Belliſarius,</hi> that great and moſt victorious Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that ſo ſolicitous and effectual was his care of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen that no violence or wrong was ever done to any one of them by any ſouldier under his conduct or command; I'le add but one inſtance more, even he who hath ſo prodigiouſly advanced his Empire by ſpoil and ruine, he who hath been eſteemed, even to a Proverb. <hi>Barbareus;</hi> the great Turk, is yet obſerved (by the moſt<note n="*" place="margin">S. A. Blunt.</note> judicious of modern Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers) to take a ſpecial and moſt exact care for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Husbandry; for he divides all his Countries among his <hi>Timariots,</hi> who are but his Yeomanry, upon whom he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows <hi>Timars</hi> or <hi>Teuds,</hi> not only that they may awe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, but alſo couſe the land to be well till'd and cul ivat; And theſe <hi>Timariots</hi> (or Yeomen) themſelves, that their Farms may be well managed, held up the Farmers with much care. It were eaſie to add unto theſe the conſenting ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Nations more eivilized, which are both copious and magnificent.</p>
            <p>But what need I multiply the Teſtimonies of men, to aſſert the honour and reſpect that alwaies hath been, and alwaies ſhall be due to Husbandry? Since God himſelf hath been, pleaſed to publiſh his moſt ſacred reſpects unto it, as many other ways, ſo particularly, by that ſtrict and proviſionary care which he hath taken for the protection of the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour pieces of it: He would not allow ſo much as a fruit Tree to be ſpoyled;<note n="*" place="margin">Deue. 20.19.</note> 
               <hi>When thou ſhalt beſiege a City, a long time in making war againſt it, to take it, thou ſhalt not deſtroy the Trees thereof: For, thou mayſt eat of them, and thou ſhalt not cut them down, &amp;c.</hi> And Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in that brief model of Prayer, doth not obſcurely inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the reſpects we owe unto the Husbandman, when he ranks this in the middle of thoſe jew Peritions which he would have us to put up daylie to our heavenly Father, <hi>Give
<pb facs="tcp:118393:4"/>us this day our daylie Bread;</hi> Which unleſs we underſtand it in a myſtical or miraculous ſenſe only, doth in my opinion clearly appoint us to pray daylie for the Husbandman, by whom God does ordinarily diſpenſe that ſtaff and ſupport of life. This is every man's duty, this ſhall be my practiſe, as to ſpeak well of you, ſo to ſpeak as well as I can for you; And this alſo directs me how to conclude at this time; Beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you All to accept this Sermon, as the firſt publike Eſſay of my Chriſtian reſpects, and exalted affections towards you; and beſeeching the All-ſufficient God, to direct, bleſs, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and defend you, in all your lawful labours, and laborious imployments.<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>Now he that miniſtreth ſeed to the Sower both miniſter bread for your food, and multiply your ſeed ſown, and increaſe the fruit of your Righteouſneſs.</hi> So prays he who is indeed one of the moſt unworthy Labourers in the Lords Harveſt, But</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very real Friend, and affectionate Servant. <hi>Nath. Newbury.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:118393:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118393:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached to Some, AND Dedicated to All the Yeomen and Farmers of KENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 CHRON. 26.10.</bibl>
                  <p>For he loved HUSBANDRY.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Text is a juſt Apology for our Meeting at this time; For if it be demanded why I preach, or why you hear this day; the anſwer is as plain as affectionate; <hi>For he loved Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think I may not unfitly call this Text <hi>The Yeomans Prerogative,</hi> or <hi>The Honour of Husbandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Husbandry</hi> is a word that doth equally refer to the Yeoman, and the Farmer; for it is the foundation, ſupport,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118393:6"/>and employment of them both; as they alſo are the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental ſupport of the Nation and Country where they live.</p>
            <p>Husbandry then is the ſubject which I intend to inſiſt on at this time; and that not in reference to the practiſe, but to the preheminence of it: As for the practiſe of Husbandry, I muſt invert that of the Prophet <hi>Zechariah, cap.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>I belong to the Schools of the Prophets;</hi> I am no Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor hath any man taught me to keep Cattle from my youth. It would be as impertinent for a Scholar to diſcourſe of the exerciſe of Husbandry before ſo many well exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Farmers, as it was for <hi>Phormio</hi> (that petulant Oratour) to diſcourſe the Diſcipline and Managery of War in the preſence of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> one of the moſt experienced Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals in the world. But for the Preheminence and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Husbandry, if I ſhould not endeavour ſo to ſpeak, as that I may diſcover my own, and attract the love of others, to ſo ancient and noble a Profeſſion; I ſhould both contradict the reality of my own affections, and deface the beauty of that Royal Certificate which one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and beſt Kings of the world hath ſubſcribed to in the Text; <hi>For, he loved Husbandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now that I may not ill husband that time which your courteous patience doth farm out unto me; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod I ſhall uſe in the Husbandry of my Sermon, ſhall be no other then that of the Husbandman.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, I ſhall Plow up the ground of my diſcourſe, in the explication of the Text.</item>
               <item>Secondly, I ſhall Sowe it with the ſpiritual ſeed of ſome ſeaſonable Doctrinal deductions, taken out of the Seed-cot of God's Word.</item>
               <item>And thirdly, I ſhall Harrow and cover the ſeed, with ſome perticent Application.</item>
            </list>
            <p>It muſt be the Dew of Divine grace and the influence of Heavens bleſſing, that muſt cauſe all to thrive and flouriſh: and then ſhall that of the Prophet <hi>Zechariah, ch.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 12.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118393:6"/>be the joyful Harveſt: <hi>For the ſeed ſhall be proſperous, the ground ſhall give her increaſe, and the heavens ſhall give their dew; and God will cauſe the remnant of this people to poſſeſs all theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave then, firſt, To bring in my plow, to lay open the ground of my ſubſequent diſcourſe. And here indeed I meet with a ground that is ſo mellow and tender, the terms of the Text, ſo eaſie and obvious, that I ſhall not need to draw a deep Furrow. A ſhallow reach, and a weak ſtrength (anſwerable to my ſtock and abilities will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to turn up the bottome of the ſenſe of theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For]</hi> This word gives us an account of thoſe undertakings which we read of in the precedent part of the verſe. It is a term of cauſality, and it is placed here but to open the gate for us into the field. The field is well ſcituated, well feaced, well ſtock'd; as you may eaſily perceive, if you pleaſe but to ſurvey the fore-going words. <hi>He built Towers</hi> (He kept good Fences) <hi>He digged Wells,</hi> (or cut out many Ciſterns or Ponds for the watering of his cattel. Indeed the meaneſt Husbandman, whether Farmer or Graſier, knows as well as the higheſt Poet,<note n="*" place="margin">Pindar.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the advantageous neceſſitity of Water; and therefore if his grounds be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally dry and parſimonious, he ſpares no coſt nor pains to draw it out, by ſinking ponds and wells) for, <hi>he had much Cattel</hi> (He was well ſtock'd) <hi>both in the low Country and in the Plains</hi> (they are places convenient, and fit for paſturage) <hi>Husbandmen alſo in the fruitful fields,</hi> or <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel</hi> (there's his diſcreet care to diſpoſe his grounds and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants according to their moſt proper capacity, <hi>Non omnis fert omnia tellus;</hi> He employs therefore his Vine-dreſſers in the mountains; places moſt open to the beams of the ſun; and his Husbandmen in <hi>Carmel,</hi> or the fruitful fields; places moſt fit for, and propitious to corn) theſe you all know are main pieces of good husbandry. The moſt obſtinate labour in plowing, ſowing weeding &amp;c. is but in vain, if the ground be not fit and kindly, the fences well kept, and the ſtock pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118393:7"/>Our compleat Husbandman, according to the greatneſs of his ability both for wiſdom and wealth did abundantly provide for all theſe neceſſary adjuncts <hi>He built</hi> &amp;c. And why all this? <hi>For he loved Husbandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He]</hi> What was He? No leſs then a King; <hi>Uzziah,</hi> a Prince famous for Piety and Proſperity; as you may ſee him deſcribed in this former part of the chapter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For Piety, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5. <hi>He did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord; And he ſought God in the days of Zechariah, who had underſtanding in the Viſions of God:</hi> See how obſervant a great Prince is of a good Miniſter, and how uſeful a good Miniſter is to a great Prince; Nor is his piety unrewarded. Indeed Piety towards God is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all true and durable happineſs amongſt men: It appear'd ſo eminently in the affairs of this Prince whoſe pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and proſperity, like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> twins, did thrive together, and together languiſh; He continues famous.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for Proſperity; as it follows in the latter part of <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>As long as he ſought the Lord, God made him to proſper.</hi> I muſt not make a balk in this place, but muſt ſadly acquaint you, that this great and good Prince did afterward decline in both; <hi>Uzziah</hi> degenerated into <hi>Uzzah;</hi> He invaded the Miniſterial Office, and violently maintain'd his intruſion, until an exemplary and convincing judgement removed him from it, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 18, 19, 20. You know the richeſt grounds are moſt ſubject to the blaſt; His proſperity over-heated him, and blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his piety with pride; and that cauſed God to ſtrike him with the mildew of a Leproſie, ſo that he pined away <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with grief and deſpondency of ſpirit, as <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> hath recorded it. Be it ſo, I deſire not to excuſe his ſin, nor to extenuate his ſuffering; yet it ſtill remains a remarkable truth. That he was a Prince very proſperous a long time, even all the while he continued pious; for <hi>as long as he ſought the Lord, God made him to proſper;</hi> and his proſperity is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed 3. ways. 1. By his military performances &amp; martial ſucceſſes. 2. By his Civil acts and undertakings; and 3. By his private &amp; family employments</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118393:7"/>
            <p>Firſt, His Martial performances and ſucceſſes, may be reduced under foure glorious Enſigns.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Victory over his Enemies;</hi> This is the red Enſigne, which you may ſee diſplayed in ſeveral Nations and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>He warred againſt the Philiſtins;</hi> and ſo far prevailed, that he took and diſmantled their chief forts, and ſtrongeſt Towns; for <hi>he brake down the wal of Gath, and the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Aſhdod: and he built Cities about Aſhdod, and among the Philiſtins;</hi> no queſtion, for gariſons, to bridle and awe that ſtout and perpetually turbulent people. And well might he prevail againſt them; for <hi>God helped him againſt the Philiſtins, and againſt the Arabians, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Preſents;</hi> or rather <hi>tribute from neighbour Nations.</hi> This is the yellow or golden colour'd Enſign, which is furl'd up; <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>the Ammonites gave gifts to Vzziah.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Renown, Fame, and Reputation abroad,</hi> This may be the white Enſign, which you may ſee flying, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>his name ſpread abroad, even to the entring in of Egyot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Exceeding ſtrength and forces.</hi> And let this be the black Enſigne: for, it was this made him ſo puiſſant and formidable: <hi>For he ſtrengthned himſelf exceedingly, v.</hi> 8. His particular ſtrength you may read more diſtinctly exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifyed, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. And as he was thus renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for military abilities and archievements, ſo</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly, For his civil undertakings. His care to build, repaire, fortifie, is hinted at <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>He built Eloth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored it to Judah;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 9. he built, repaired, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the chief out-parts of Jeruſalem. And</p>
            <p>Thirdly. His private and family imployments were thoſe which are ſpecifyed at the 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> the verſe of our text.</p>
            <p>So that he is repreſented, a Prince happy in all the parts of humane affairs. Military, Political, and Oeconomical; in Campe, City and Country buſineſs, happy; and yet behold, ſo potent prudent and ſucceſſeful a prince, thought it no diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to manage the affaires of husbandry. It is recorded
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118393:8"/>to his honour, and as a ſpeciall part of his happineſs; that <hi>he built, and digged, and had much cattel, and husbandmen, &amp;c. For he loved husbandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Loved]</hi> He delighted in it; he was not neceſſitated, or enforced to it, he found much comfort, quiet, content in it; it is no queſtion, but he had his Bayliffes, and Farmers under him; <hi>but</hi> himſelf diſdayned not to over-ſee, provide for, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, encourage, ſupport them; again, <hi>he loved it,</hi> he was not like envious <hi>Ahab,</hi> he repined not at his thriving neighbours, but cheerfully purſued the improvement of his own lands; and rather then he would deturbe or turn any of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects out of their poſſeſſions, he procured paſturage for his cattel a far off; and this is hinted in that word, <hi>in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerto,</hi> in the deſert, <hi>i.e. Arabia, quod paſcuoſum erat,</hi> as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> notes upon the place; <hi>The deſert of Arabia had good paſturage;</hi> ſo that he neither diſdained husbandry, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged husbandmen, but did greatly honour, encourage, delight in both. <hi>For he loved Husbandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Husbandry]</hi> All ſorts of it, planting, graffing; but more particularly, Agriculture, Tillage; the nature of which you all know ſo much better then my ſelf, that I will not be ſo vainly preſumptuous, as to miſpend either my diſcretion or time in the deſcription of it; nor is it my intention to read you a lecture out of <hi>Virgil's Georgicks, or Markhams husbandry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I Plowed up this little piece of ground, and (I hope) drawn a ſtreight, though no deep furrow, through every part of the Text, in this plain explication; I come now,</p>
            <p>Secondly, to <hi>Sow</hi> it, with ſome ſeaſonable doctrinal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions: and here I muſt go over the ground again, and I meet but with three ridges, which are fit to be ſown.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1, Here's a cauſal particle. <hi>For,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An honorary or commendatory relative; <hi>He.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The terme of complacency, which is as the ſod-acre, upon which all turnes, <hi>Loved.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Husbanary,</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> terme, is as the whole field it ſelf, that is to be ſowen upon, and without any forcing, it will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118393:8"/>bear the ſeed of theſe three doctrinall Obſervations.
<list>
                     <item>1. We may obſerve the induſtrious care, and proſperous diligence of our royall husbandman. <hi>For.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The dignity and honour of husbandry: It is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment not unworthy a King, <hi>He.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The affectionate delight and delightfull affection wherewith he followed his buſineſs; <hi>Loved. For he loved husbandry.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of theſe briefly, and</p>
            <p>Firſt, let us obſerve the care and diligence of our diſcreete husbandman; induſtrious diligence in providing for, and contriving the moſt advantagious managery of his affairs, is a prime requiſite in a thriving husbandman: that which is Generally propounded by <hi>Salomon. Prov.</hi> 10.4. <hi>He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemmeth poor that dealeth with a ſlack hand, but the hand of the diligent maketh rich;</hi> may be eminently taken notice of, as a ſpecial rule in our husbandmans buſineſs; lazy, or ſlothful, and letty, or hinderly are words of the ſame impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in your common expreſſions; diligence and riches are as <hi>Bernard</hi> phraſes it in another caſe, <hi>Virtutes collactaneae,</hi> Foſter ſiſters, nurs'd up by the divine providence ſuckled and nouriſhed with the ſweeteſt milk of the indulgent earth; nor is it improbable that <hi>Salmon</hi> intended this obſervation more particularly for the husbandman, if we conſider what he adds, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>He that gathereth in ſummer, is a wiſe ſon; but he that ſleepeth in harvest, is a ſon that cauſeth ſhame.</hi> And I think that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10. is not only an apoſtolical dictate, but a prophetical denunciation alſo: <hi>that if any man would not work, neither ſhould he eat;</hi> and he may thereby, as preſcribe the penalty, ſo foretell the penury of idle buſy bodies; that as they ought not to have any, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordinarily is it likely that they ſhould have their own bread to eate, if they will not labour. However, we have here before us a princely pattern and patron of judicious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry; <hi>Vzziah,</hi> thought not the eminency of his place, not the largeneſs of his revenues, could priviledge or exempt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118393:9"/>him from the labour and trouble of domeſtical buſineſs; he is as eminent in induſtry, as in dignity: his chargeable care about fencing, and watring his grounds; his diſcreet diſpoſal of his ſervants, &amp;c. is recommended to us, and we are invited to reflect, on it by this cauſall particle, <hi>for;</hi> when he had once applyed himſelf to husbandry, he quickly had his hands and head full of imployment; he is fain to build and fence, and dig, and look after ſtock, and entertain hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, <hi>for he loved &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>David</hi> alſo, the nobleſt of his royal Anceſtors, when his Kingdom was throughly ſetled, provides for the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and wiſe ordering of his husbandry affairs; he diſpoſes Bayliffs and Overſeers for all ſorts of husbandry; the holy Ghoſt hath been pleaſed to record their names in that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſhable hiſtory of his moſt memorable actions, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 27.26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. For his <hi>Tillage, Ezri;</hi> for his <hi>planted ground, Shimei, and Baalhanan;</hi> for his <hi>Pasturage</hi> and <hi>Grazing, Shetvai, Shaphat, and Jaziz. All theſe were the rulers of the ſubſtance, that was King Davids.</hi> Thus the care of Chriſt ouer his church, is allegorically repreſented, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.2. <hi>he feneed it, and gathered out the ſtones thereof, and planted it, &amp;c.</hi> and when he had been at ſuch charges, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſo much pains with it, he might juſtly expect, it ſhould yeild him a proportionable increaſe; if it do not, let the blame light where it will, it cannot be charged upon him, let who wil judge. <hi>What could have been done more unto my vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, that I have not done in it. v.</hi> 4. A ſedulous diligence, is all that Chriſt will do in the husbandry of his Church. I am ſure it is all that man can do in the husbandry of his grounds; he that would interced for the fruitleſs vineyard had nothing to plead, but that he might be allowed to try the utmoſt of his skill and pains upon it; <hi>Luke</hi> 13.8. <hi>Lord, let it alone this yeer alſo, till I ſhall dig about it, and dung it and if it, bear fruit, well, &amp;c.</hi> It may be there are ſome grounds, that will obſtinately contemn the husbandmans induſtry, and unkindly delude his moſt juſt and patient hopes; yet undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118393:9"/>it is true, what <hi>Menochius</hi> in his ſacred Oeconomicks, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20, obſerves, <hi>Illud generatum tenendum eſt, multum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrii, &amp; ſeduli agricolae diligentiam poſſe, eum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> qui agrum ſuum opportuno tempore verſaverit &amp;c. facturum opera pretium.</hi> Generally the husbandmans care and diligence in plowing, ſowing, weeding, &amp;c. wiil gratefully return into his barnes, with a plenteous recompence of his labour; yea, a ſeaſonable induſtry can work miracles; it can turn ſtones in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bread, and make barrenneſs it ſelfe fruitful. So that (as God is pleaſed prophetically to expreſs the admirable fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of a mountainous and rugged land, <hi>'Deut.</hi> 32.13. our induſtrious husbandman ſhall prevailingly and triumphant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ride on the high and most ſtubborn places of the earth, he ſhall eat the increaſe of the fields, he ſhall ſuck hony out of the rock, and oyl out of the flinty rock.</hi> His labour may be hard, but it ſhall be happy; and ſo much for the preſent of our husbandmans humble induſtry; which as it is the ready, though narrow road to honour and dignity, ſo it doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly lead me into the next Obſervation, which is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The dignity and honour of Husbandry; <hi>He, Vzziah,</hi> a prince, thinks it not unworthy his care and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance; indeed husbandry is an imployment, that the beſt of men have undertaken, throughout all countrys, in all ages; an imployment, that the nobleſt ſpirits have not been aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of. It was the only imployment which God thought fit for, and becomming the moſt excellent of his creatures in the ſtate of innocency. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.15. <hi>And the Lord God took the man, and put him into the garden of Eden, to dreſs it; ad colendum eum,</hi> to husband it, as <hi>Junius</hi> tranſlates, <hi>proſciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, irrigatione, fatione, &amp; ſiqua ſunt ejuſmodi.</hi> by digging, watering ſowing it, and the like acts of good husbandry to winn &amp; procure of it thoſe herbs, and ſeeds or grain which God had deſigned for the food of man; <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.16. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which alſo we may obſerve, that thoſe fruits of the earth provided for the ſuſtentation of man, may claim the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Birth-right before the Sun and Moon, as being a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118393:10"/>day elder; <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.11. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. Now as <hi>Adam</hi> was put upon this employment by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo <hi>Noah</hi> the Father of the ſecond world, choſe this calling, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 9.20. <hi>And</hi> Noah <hi>began to be an Husbandman.</hi> i.e. <hi>diligentius quam ante dil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vium,</hi> to ſet himſelf about that buſineſs more ſtrenuouſly and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly than they needed to do before the Flood; becauſe as <hi>Lapide in locum</hi> obſerves, that deluge, by the ſaltneſs, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſharpneſs, and fluctuating motion of the water, had drawn forth, and much waſted the Primitive goodneſs and fatneſs of the earth: True it is, that by the firſt penal ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute enacted after <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall, grievous and hard labour was required of our Husbandman, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.17. Yet it muſt needs be, that this additional ſterility with which the Flood infected the earth, did alſo neceſſitate man to ſorer travel and labour. Well therefore might <hi>Noah</hi> be ſaid to begin to be an Husbandman, as being the firſt that imployed the utmoſt of his Art and Skill, (as well as pains and induſtry) in the Husbandry of the ground. The ancient Heathen attributed the invention of the Plough to <hi>Oſyris,</hi> now <hi>Pererius, Delrie,</hi> and other learned Criticks conceive, that by this <hi>Oſyris</hi> was meant <hi>Noah.</hi> And whereas before the Flood, <hi>manibus &amp; ligonibus terram foederent,</hi> they prepared the earth with the tedious handy-labour of the Spade; that <hi>Noah</hi> was the man, who to the great eaſe and advantage of man-kind, found out the artifice and uſe of Ploughs, as alſo their draught by horſe and oxen: The Heads and Princes of his poſterity, <hi>Sem, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> and afterward <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob, Booz,</hi> &amp;c. ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in this calling; yea after they attained the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power, they did not decline the affairs of Husbandry. <hi>Saul</hi> forſook not his old imployment, as appears, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.5. And <hi>Saul</hi> came after <hi>armentum ſuum,</hi> his own herd out of the field: <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Uzziah</hi> were mentioned before. And if we look out of the ſacred, into other Hiſtories, they abound in illuſtrious examples to this purpoſe; <hi>Cyrus</hi> the Perſian, <hi>Diocleſian Juſtin,</hi> and other Roman Emperors; <hi>Hiero, Philo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118393:10"/>metor, Attalus, Archelaus,</hi> and many Grecian Kings were Husbandmen; the Nobleſt families in the Roman Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, were founded upon Husbandry, as appears by their Titles and names: Hence the <hi>Fabij, Lentuli, Piſones, Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones, Vitellij, Porrij, Servij, Appij,</hi> and others; to which very many Gentilitious names among us are parallel; as <hi>Bean, Lentil, Peas, Chickly, Yokely, Swinford, Plonden, Wheatly,</hi> &amp;c. The moſt excellent Chieftains of the world, have been taken from the Fold, or the Stall, or the Plough; <hi>Moſes</hi> a Shepherd, <hi>Exodus</hi> 3.1. <hi>Gideon</hi> a Threſher, <hi>Judges</hi> 6.11. <hi>Val. Maximus,</hi> and <hi>Dioniſius Halicar</hi> ſpeak of <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talus, Quintus, Curius,</hi> and others; who were fetched from the Plough to the Conſulſhip, yea Dictatorſhip, in ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent difficulty of affairs, and diſtreſs of their country; and that after they had faithfully, magnanimouſly, and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately diſcharged thoſe great offices, they cheerfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their Husbandry buſineſs. What ſhall I ſay more? <hi>Eliſha</hi> that great Prophet, was at firſt but a rich Ploughman, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19.19. Two of the Apoſtles, <hi>Janies</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> were Husbandmen, as <hi>Clem. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Conſtit. Apoſt. cap.</hi> 63. has recorded it. And therefore they do ſo frequently in their Epiſtles make uſe of compariſons drawn from their own calling, as of trees, plants, fruits of the earth, &amp;c. Yea, Chriſt himſelf ſeems to have been much delighted with ſuch ſimilitudes: He compares himſelf to a Seedſman. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.5. And the Father accepts the appellation of an Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.1. Nor refuſes he the practiſe of Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, <hi>verſe</hi> 2. How doth not all this conduce much to the honour and dignity of Husbandry? That it is a calling of immediately Divine Inſtitution, a calling that hath been uſed by the beſt and Nobleſt of men in all ages, a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that hath given a name and imployment to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; who can chuſe but honour and love ſuch a calling? and that's it I am next to ſpeak to.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The affection of our Husbandman to, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency and delight in his calling; <hi>He loved.</hi> Husbandry is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118393:11"/>a calling that deſerves the deareſt love, and moſt affectionate reſpects of all men; both of thoſe who imployed and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in it, and of all others.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It deſerves the love, and requires the delight of all ſuch as practiſe it, and that among others for theſe 4. reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For it laboriouſneſs and difficulty. It is no eaſie, no ſlight, no lazy employment. We ordinarily obſerve, that the Husbandmans buſineſs is never at an end, and that he hath but two ſleeping nights in the whole yeer. Undoubtedly he labours under the influence of that Divine Edict, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. <hi>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat bread, till thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the ground,</hi> even unto that ground over which thou haſt taken ſo many weary turns. All his life he finds that to be a practical truth, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>All things are full of labour, man cannot utter it.</hi> Now it is love to it, and delight in it, that can ſweeten his labour, ſhorten his way, alienate and eaſe the weight and burthen of his employments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For its emolument and profitableneſs;</p>
            <p>This compenſates his labour. How many ſubſtantial Families do originally owe their inheritances to husbandry? It is ſaid of <hi>Iſſachar, Gen.</hi> 49.14.15. <hi>Iſſachar as a ſtrong Aſs, couching down between two burdens; and he ſaw her Reſt was good, and the land was pleaſant, and bowed his ſhoulder to bear, and become a ſervant unto Tribute.</hi> Upon which place, I like not <hi>Junius</hi> his note; <hi>Licet robuſtiſſimus ſit, nihil praeclari geret; ſed d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> deſideus ignavit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tributa ir dici patietur.</hi> That through ſloth, he would not perform any honourable and hazardous attempt, but would rather ſlaviſhly ſubmit to be a Tributary. This note, I ſay, I conceive to be impertinent, becauſe that prediction of his Father was delivered as his bleſſing not his diſgrace; and it appears that he was not of ſuch a ſervile nature, but that he could do valiantly when juſt occaſion was offered; for he willingly came in to help <hi>Barack</hi> in that dangerous battel againſt <hi>Siſera, Judg.</hi> 5.15. And therefore I approve the obſervation of our learned and ingenious Countryman<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Th. Fuller</hi> in his Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gah ſight of <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> Book 2. cap. 7.</note> That
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118393:11"/>
               <hi>Iſſachar</hi> is reſembled to an Aſs, not for the ſtupidity of his head, but for the ſtrength of his back; and it ſeems he had wiſdom as well as ſtrength; for this Tribe is taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of for an excellent piece of skill and diſcretion; 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 12.32. <hi>The children of Iſſachar were men that had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the times, to know what Iſrael ought to do.</hi> They were not only weatherwiſe, as <hi>Rivet</hi> would have it but good Chronologers, yea diſcreet Stateſmen able by obſervation of former, to make out directions for future times. However, this Tribe afforded the beſt Yeomandry in Iſrael, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced moſt towards rates and aſſeſsments: The two bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens forementioned, were Taxes and Tillage; which they ſenſible of the goodneſs of their ſoyl, and the profits that came in by their Country employments, and peacefull labours, did willingly and wiſely ſubmit unto. And ſurely it is a piece of inſolent indiſcretion, for any man to repine at the payment of a ſhilling to ſave a pound eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when he hath his life and livelyhood, his peace and quiet attendance upon his calling ſecured to him into the bargain. Iſſachar though compared to an aſs had more wit for upon obſervation of the advantages, that redounded to him by a quiet attendance upon his husbandry buſineſs, he bowed his ſhoulder to beare, and cheerfully became a ſervant to tribute.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For its Salubrity and healthfulneſs, no imployment conduces more to the health and vigour of the body, than Husbandry. It is too true indeed, and to be bewail'd, that the cuſtomary luxury of Towns and Cities, hath tainted too many of the Country, and ſo drawn them to partake of their diſeaſes, as they do of their diſſoluteneſs; but for ſuch as are abſtemious and keep themſelves generally to their Country diet ſuch as are reſident upon, and diligent in their Country employments, how many have there been that have outlived whole Towns and Cities? Our northern Countryman old <hi>Parr,</hi> may be one inſtance; Undoubtedly thoſe people who are fartheſt removed from the fortneſs and luxury of Courts
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118393:12"/>and Cities, and in a manner obliged to hard labor, and home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fare, are ſeldom acquainted with thoſe high and mighty diſeaſes of the Gout, Stone &amp;c. but have the hardneſs of their labour, and the ſhortneſs of their diet, plentifully recompenc'd with the length healthfulneſs and ſalubrity of their lives.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For its tranquility and peacefulneſs. How have not many, (who were tyred and wearyed with the brawls and ſtrifes, the deceipts and cozenages of Court and City) rety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto this life, for the calm and ſettlement of their ſouls and eſtates? <hi>Aeneas Sylvius, Hiſt. Bohem. c.</hi> 13. tels of one <hi>Suatocopius</hi> a Bohemian King, who being worſted by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulph</hi> the Emperor in Battel, retyred to a private country life; and having lived long unknown in this Sanctuary when he lay on his death bed, he ſent for his neighbour villagers, and profeſſed unto them, <hi>Ego ſum Rex Bohemiae, &amp;c.</hi> I am a King, I have fully tryed both the Court and the Country life, and dying, I now pronounce, that there is no life valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto this, for quiet peacefulneſs, and tranquility, which is indeed the very life of our lives. The laſt century hath furniſhed us with a more memorable example, <hi>Charls</hi> the 5. Emperor of <hi>Germany</hi> L. of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> did voluntarily reſign all his Kingdoms and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and put himſelf into a ſmall Country houſe of ſeven rooms, and a little garden, where he ſpent the remainder of his years in riding about the grounds with one ſervant, in quartering his garden into little beds in ſetting Flowers and planting Trees with his own hands, and acknowledg'd that he enjoy'd more ſolid pleaſure and content in that his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate country ſolitude, then he had done all his life before in all his victories and triumphs. How ſhall not our Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man love that life that is ſo lovely, and affords ſo many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations? And as Husbandry deſerves the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans love, ſo doth it alſo the love and reſpect.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of all other men, for three Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For its Antiquity I am not ignorant that a plea from meer antiquity, is but a ſimple ſophiſme; our ſimple nature is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118393:12"/>called the old man, yet is not therefore to be cheriſhed; the Devil was a murtherer from the begining, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. and the Church makes humble confeſſion, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 106.9. <hi>We have er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with our Fathers.</hi> It was but the ſtubbornneſs of the Jews to plead, <hi>We will do as our Fathers. Jer.</hi> 44.17. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny practiſes are very old, yet very erroneous; many old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and old doings muſt be unſaid, and undone, or we ſhall be undon for ever. How many old ſayings of the Jews doth Chriſt gainſay, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Ye have heard that it hath been ſaid by them of old time</hi> thus and thus. <hi>But I ſay unto you, &amp;c.</hi> I well know (as one ſayes) that wiſdom doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies lean upon a ſtaff, nor look through ſpectacles: Nor would I be eſteemed ſo ſhallow, as to draw up an argument from the Gibeonitiſh antiquity of mouldy bread &amp; clouted ſhoes; but where antiquity is duly circumſtantiated, in things uſeful and excellent it is ſurely venerable and may claim a due reſpect: We are bid, <hi>Ier.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Enquire for the good old way;</hi> ſuch is that which I propound to your reſpect upon this ground, in a civil ſenſe Husbandry is the good old way that God himſelf appointed for the ſuſtentation and imployment of man-kind; and what the Apoſtle ſpeaks in commendation of the commandment, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2, 7. I may apply to this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, this is the old calling which was from the beginning, Husbandry is abſolutely the moſt antient inſtituted imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it began with man and the world, and hath together with man &amp; the world been perpetually continued through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages, without interruption: The moſt ſubtile of the ambitious Gentiles, could fetch the antientary of their gods and Heroes, no further then from <hi>Tellus,</hi> and <hi>Ops, Rhea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alex. Roſs.</note> and <hi>Veſta,</hi> by which (as our ingenious Mythologer obſerves) they meant the earth. And theſe Nations who would boaſt their deſcent upon this Principle of venerable antiquity, as the <hi>Accadians</hi> cal'd themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genae</hi> the Off-ſpring or ſons of the earth; and acknowledged <hi>Pan</hi> a Shepherd, their founder and Father. They had but a glimmering of what we know to be a clear truth; and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Husbandman was our Original Anceſtor, and Husbandry
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118393:13"/>the prime imployment of the Father of us all: We ſhould love it for that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For its innocency and harmleſneſs. <hi>Agricultura ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium omnium innocentiſſima;</hi> It is <hi>Auguſtines</hi> obſervation: that husbandry is the moſt harmleſs of all imployments, arts or trades, moſt otherwiſe in the world, men live and thrive, either by undermining, undervaluing, or by over-powring, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver flattering overſelling overreaching others: but the returns which the husbandmans fields and flocks bring in, are no ways prejudicial many ways profitable to others as well as himſelf. Our husbandman doth not envy others but lives well pleaſed with what providence gives him; he is free from all fretting cares, and is fed with no mans proviſions but his own; the crop of his land comes in once a yeer and it is got with a good conſcience but (as the judicious Spaniard,<note place="margin">Guevara.</note> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently dilates upon this argument) he that ſeeks after places of eminency, in Courts or Citys, will be ſure to find envy and competitors, frequent diſſimulation, dangerous reſervednes, an evil ey, ridiculous affectation, policie, revenge, ſupercilious ſcorns, a phantaſtick gate, ſplendid and ſelling words, groſs calumny curſing, ſwearing, (which could make a good chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an wiſh himſelf deaf) with ambition the moſt poyſonous weed of the mind, are the plants which grow in thoſe gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens: our humble &amp; contented husbandman, by Gods bleſſing upon his labours, thrives by an honeſt induſtry, without ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting his neighbour, while others out of an unfatiable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, by rapine and oppreſſion, maintain their abominable greatneſs with the blood &amp; tears of poor innocents and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans; &amp; like harpies &amp; heathens, take the bread out of the mouths, of the helpleſs &amp; harmleſs children. O how innocent are the advancements of husbandry! It deſervs the diſcreet encouragement of your moſt reſpectful affection if it be but for its advantageous inoffenſiveneſs; and much more.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For its univerſal uſefulneſs, yea abſolute neceſſity; and here indeed the husbandman may juſtly tryumph; for I muſt in his behalf confidently affirm, there is not in all the world any other temporal, manual imployment ſo indiſpenſably uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118393:13"/>and neceſſary for humane life and ſubſiſtence, as Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry. Let any impartial man run over all other Manual Trades and Callings, in his moſt ſerious thoughts, and I doubt not but they will appear to bee either the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren or Nurſes of Wealth, Pride, Vanity, Luxury, or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity: Or if ſome few others be for Conveniency, yea, and reſpective Neceſſity, (as I know ſome others both Mercurial, Martial, and Mechanical are, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the preſent poſture of the affairs of the world,) yet I muſt ſtill conclude, that This, this Calling only, is of abſolute Neceſſity: Sure I am, we might all comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſerve our God and our Generation, upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions ſpecified in <hi>Jacobs</hi> Indentures, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20. <hi>If God will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me Bread to eat, and Raiment to put on.</hi> Now Husbandry alone, (with Gods bleſſing) is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly able to ſupply both theſe Neceſſaries. Let not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man miſtake me; I intend not any word or ſentence that I delive upon this Subject, in a Levelling deſtructive ſenſe, I do onely purſue the argument I have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a rational way: To that purpoſe I entreat every unprejudiced man, to conſider theſe two adverſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, which will jointly concur to aſſert the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Neceſſity of Husbandry.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This Calling can ſubſiſt without any others: as for the Forge and the Axe, I eſteem them but as ſervants and appurtenances of Husbandry; Now if all other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments from the rich Merchant to the poor Pedlar, were vaniſhed out of the world, the Husbandman were able to make a ſufficient, yea comfortable proviſion for the Nations; He did ſo at firſt for ſome Ages.</p>
            <p>Secondly, No others can ſubſiſt without this. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when God would denounce ruine and deſolation to any people, he threatens to remove the ſtaffe of bred, by blaſtings, mildews, unſeaſonable weather, and other
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118393:14"/>calamities upon the Husbandmans affairs, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.26.32 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.16. and 5. c. 16. v. <hi>The evil arrows of Famine, ſhall be for their deſtruction;</hi> and Ezek. 14.13. <hi>When the Land ſinneth againſt me, then will I ſtretch out my hand upon it, and will break the ſtaffe of the bread thereof, and will cut off man and beaſt from it.</hi> I conclude this with the acknowledgement of the wiſeſt King, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.9. <hi>The profit of the Earth is for all, the King himſelf is ſerved by the Field,</hi> or <hi>the King alſo conſiſteth by the field that is tilled;</hi> upon which the <hi>Geneva</hi> Note is this. The revenues of the Earth are to be preferred above all things which appertain to this life; For the greateſt Princes and States cannot maintain their Eſtate without Tillage.</p>
            <p>And thus have I performed the ſecond part of my promiſe: I have ſcattered the ſeed of ſome Doctrinal Obſervations, over all the Furrows of this little Field; I hope I have made choice of ſeed that was proper and kindly for the ground: Now that it may root well and proſper, I doubt not but you will give me leave,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To cover all that I have ſown, with the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of Application. You know that there is a twofold uſe of the Harrow, To break the clods, draw off the graſſe and weeds, which would hinder the rooting and ſpringing, or choak the growth of the Corn; and to cover, keep ſafe and warm the ſeed: I ſhall make uſe of the Harrow both ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To break the clods, and draw off the weeds, in a Uſe of Reprehenſory Conviction. You have heard ſomewhat of the Excellency, Lovelineſs, and Neceſſity of Husbandry: What now will thoſe proud and ſcornfull Gallants anſwer, who make the very word Plowman, (which ſpeaks a better imployment then they themſelves ordinarily are acquainted with) a tearm of ſcorn and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain? What will they now ſay, who deride and contemn the painful, uſeful, peaceful, yea indeed truly Honourable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118393:14"/>Husbandman, when they ſhal underſtand the high eſteem which the nobleſt and wiſeſt of men have had of him? I hope none will prevent what I ſhall ſpeak, as if it were in my thoughts to caſt dirt upon the Gentry, who are the Splendor and Glory of a flouriſhing Nation: I know the Heaven hath many ſtars which appear chiefly for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, yet are not without their uſe and influence: I have obſerved that truly generous ſpirits, are like a ſword of the beſt tempered metal, moſt flexible and pliable, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable and courteous in behavior to their Inferiours; Nor do I doubt but that all underſtanding Gentlemen, doe ſufficiently know and accordingly value the worth of the Husbandman. I reflect not upon theſe: but it is to the proud and idle, the ſcornful and contemptuous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (who hath little beſides a great Eſtate, and a gay ſuit of cloaths to prove his Gentility) that I now ſpeak. Thou art thy ſelf but <hi>terrae filius,</hi> a clod of Earth, or in the Language of the Prophet, (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.6.) as the graſs, and all thy pompous goodlineſs but as the flower of the Field; and flowers there, are ordinarily more noiſome to the Corn, then pleaſant to the eye: yea, I muſt tell thee that an idle and proud Gentleman, who is neither bred to, nor inclined to, nor fit for any good employment, is but a weed, perhaps the worſt weed in a Commonwealth; and if I thought it were not too bitter a cenſure, I would affirm that the lives of ſuch, I ſay of ſuch Gentlemen, are of as little uſe, and as much miſchief to a Nation, as that of idle vagrants, and ſturdy vagabonds. Nor indeed are they very much unlike; for do they not alike ſpend their time in walking up and down, eating and drinking? Doe they not alike feed on the ſweat of other mens labours, the ſweat of other mens brows? I muſt freely confeſs, that I do not yet underſtand, what prejudice it would be to the Common-wealth, if all ſuch Gentlemen, were within the compaſs of the ſame Statute for Vagrants:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118393:15"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rivet.</hi> in Gen. 3.</note> The <hi>Athenians</hi> a wiſe Commonwealth, did ſue idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at Law, idleneſs among them did bear an Action, and it was called <hi>Actio</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I am ſure they are within compaſs of that Apoſtolical Statute, 2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 3.10. <hi>This we commanded you, that if any would not work, neither ſhould he eat:</hi> For my part therefore I doe not conceive that the world would much miſs them, if there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a one of them upon the face of the Earth. Now if any man think that any of theſe expreſſions are too ſowr and ſevere, he may pleaſe to ſweeten his palate again, by taking a review of the ſame thing, as it is expreſſed by the<note n="*" place="margin">D. Donnes Letters, <hi>p. 51.</hi>
               </note> great Maſter of Engliſh wit, and language, who hath thus wrapt up this bitter pill in his golden phraſe. <hi>To bee no part of any body,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is to be nothing. At moſt the greateſt perſons are but great wens, and excreſcencies; Men of wit, and delightfull converſation, but as moles for ornament, except they be ſo incorporated into the body of the world, that they contribute ſomething to the ſuſtentation of the whole.</hi> Thou that are ſo uſeleſs, and doſt thou vilifie and deſpiſe thoſe who are ſo uſeful, ſo neceſſary? I have done with the firſt Uſe of the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the reproof of ſuch as undervalue our Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. I addreſs my ſelf now to you who love, encourage, and practiſe Husbandry.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to cover that good ſeed that hath been ſown, with a ſerious Exhortation, and ſome ſuitable directions.</p>
            <p>And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, you that are Husbandmen, I do earneſtly exhort you, to acknowledge the gracious Providence of God, in that he hath cauſed you to be bred to the moſt ancient, uſeful, and neceſſary calling in the world. I may make uſe of that of the Apoſtle, (1 Cor. 1.26.) <hi>Videte Vocatic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem veſtram,</hi> as <hi>Trem:</hi> out of the <hi>Syriack</hi> renders it, <hi>Behold, take notice of your Calling, Brethren;</hi> God hath choſen you to ſuch a Calling, as hath been adorn'd, by the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118393:15"/>wiſeſt nobleſt, and mightieſt in the world, who have both honoured it, and been practitioners in it. If the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, ſhall at any time, prefer you by it, above it, be ye never aſhamed of your beginning; <hi>David</hi> was not, though he was taken out of the Sheepfold, but even thence takes occaſion publiquely and perpetually to magnifie God, who had exalted him; Pſal 78.70, 71. <hi>He choſe</hi> David <hi>his ſervant, and took him from the Sheepfolds; from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ewes, he brought him to feed</hi> Jacob <hi>his people, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>his inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Since your Calling is ſo honourable, O bee yee careful to honour your Calling, by a ſuitable cariage, a correſpondent conveſation, and that you ſhall do, if you will but obſerve and purſue theſe ſeven directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be <hi>induſtrious</hi> in your buſineſs. Read and ponder thoſe inducements, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.11. <hi>He that gathereth by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſhall encreaſe;</hi> and ch. 14.23. <hi>In all labour there is profit, whereas ſloth is eaſily overtaken with penury.</hi> Prov. 6.9.11. <hi>O ſluggard, thy poverty ſhall come as one that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velleth,</hi> (ſuddenly, and unexpectedly) <hi>and thy want as an armed man,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> violently and irreſiſtably.) Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that God never ſet up any on his Stage of the world, for a dumb ſhew; He hath appointed all men to live, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſweat of the brain, or of the brow. Conſider farther, that diligence in your Callings ſhall be attened with unexpected bleſſings: The firſt news of a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was brought to the Shepheards, while <hi>they abode in the Field, keeping watch over their Flocks by night, Luke</hi> 2.8. Believe it, the Husbandmans induſtry, is the eaſieſt and moſt certain, if not the only true Alchimy: It can turn Earth into Gold; Induſtry is the moſt powerfull charm; It can prevail with the moſt ſtubborn ground, and cauſe it to yeild profit and increaſe. The Story of <hi>C. Furius</hi> a Roman Farmer is remarkable; He had a ſmall Farm, yet he reaped much larger Crops, and lived
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118393:16"/>better upon it, then many of his neighbors, who had grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Farms and Stocks. Upon this he is not only envied, but ſuſpected of ſorcery; that by ſome unlawful means he had bewitched his neighbors cattel, and by ſom ſtrange ſleight defeated them of their expected Crops: Hee is brought before a Magiſtrate, (I know their tearms, but I make uſe of ours) a day appointed for his Trial, he is vehemently accuſed, the Jury ready to paſs upon him; All his defence was this; He cauſed to be brought into the Court, all his Husbandry, Utenſils, Inſtruments, Plowes, &amp;c. ſubſtantially made, well fitted, and neatly kept. His ſon a robuſtious youth, in plain apparel, his draught Horſe and Oxen, luſty, full, and well dreſs'd; and only added this, <hi>Veneficia mea haec ſunt, Quirites; nec poſſum vobis oſtendere, aut in forum adducere lucubrationes vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias &amp; ſudores. Theſe, theſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are all the charms and ſorceries that I uſe, beſides the care and paines, the watchfulneſs and labour, that I am accuſtomed to night and day: And thoſe indeed I cannot at this time produce un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi> Upon which he was preſently diſcharged with the Univerſal applauſe of all preſent. Indeed, my friends, ſo it is; Care can do more then Coſt. You uſe to ſay, The Maſters eye makes the horſe fat; and truly I muſt tell you, The Maſters foot, makes the ground fruitful: be <hi>induſtrious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Be <hi>Patient:</hi> Of all men the Husbandman muſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36. <hi>Ye have need of Patience;</hi> You have need of it, in reſpect of the tediouſneſs and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſucceſſion of your labours. You have need of it, in reſpect of the frequent and unkinde deceitfulneſs of the Earth, which for much coſt and care beſtowed upon it, will too often make a very unproportionable return; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the patience which is required in an Husbandman, is extraordinary; and therefore is it propounded as exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, <hi>James</hi> 5.7. <hi>Be patient brethren, bebold the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118393:16"/>waiteth for the precious fruit of the Earth, and hath long patience for it:</hi> Again, you have need of it, that you may be enabled to bear your croſs, among all your croſſes, that of the negligence, untowardneſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs of ſervants, who are ſometimes more hard to be managed, then the moſt unruly cattel, or then the moſt cledgy Earth: be <hi>patient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Be <hi>Contented:</hi> Let not unſeaſonable weather, thin Crops, loſs of cattel, &amp;c. diſcompoſe thy humble ſoul; And becauſe thy Barns are ſometimes empty, or ſcarce half fill'd, let not thy thoughts be full of diſtruſtful care and doubts of Gods fatherly and merciful Providence; Know and ſtudy that ſhort, but ſolid principle of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Jehovah jireh, The Lord will ſee, or provide:</hi> As thou walkeſt thy Grounds, think that to be the Motto for each of thy Fields. Remember in all ſtraits that experimental preſcription, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Be content with ſuch things as you have, for he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> Con throughly that uſeful leſſon, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>J have learned in whatſoever eſtate J am there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be content, J know how to be abaſed, and how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound; Every where, and in all things J am inſtructed, both to be full, and to be hungry, both to abound, and ſuffer need. Bernard</hi> doth appoſitely call contentation, <hi>Cuſtos ſigilli,</hi> it ſeals Gods Promiſes unto our ſouls, and it ſeals up our ſouls to an holy ſubmiſſion unto Gods diſpoſal: I may call contentment the Keeper of the Liberties of the Soul, by authority of the Heavenly Parliament; It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon <hi>Parlè Dieu,</hi> God hath ſaid,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be <hi>Thankeful, Deut.</hi> 8.8, 9.10.17, 18. <hi>When God gives thee a Land of Wheat and Barley, a Land wherein thou ſhalt eat bread without ſcarceneſs; when thou haſt eaten, and art full, then thou ſhalt bleſſe the Lord thy God, for the good Land, which he hath given thee: Beware, leſt when thou art full, and when thy Heards and thy Flocks
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118393:17"/>multiply, and all that thou haſt is multiplied: Then thine heart be lifted up, and thou ſay, My power, and my care, and the might of my hand hath gotten me this wealth: But O remember the Lord thy God, for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth. When the Paſtures are cloathed with flocks, and the Valleys covered over with Corn, ſo that they ſhout for joy, Pſa.</hi> 65.13. then ſay thou alſo, as <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Praiſe waiteth for thee, O God, in my ſoul.</hi> And<note n="*" place="margin">After a long drought, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to rain at that time.</note> now me thinks that I am ſpeaking of praiſe due unto God, I ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonably prevaricate, if I ſhould not at this inſtant take notice, That whatſoever men may think of it, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſeems to approve our meeting here, in that he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſend now ſo very ſeaſonable and long deſired a Rain. Say not, it is yet but a little; That Beggar is as indiſcreet as impudent, who ſtanding in need of a ſhilling, ſhall reject a penny: A thankful acceptance of a little, is the moſt ingenious method of obtaining more. Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs is Heavens Harveſt, all the Crop that God can reap by man, for any favour beſtow'd upon him; O then, as thou reapeſt Gods bleſſings, ſo let God reap thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Otherwiſe thy very grounds, thy cattel wil condemn thee, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 1.3. <hi>The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters crib, but my people doth not conſider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is an Apologue of a poor man, who went often to a Wood to gather ſticks, where one day he found one of his rich neighbours fallen into a pit; in which was alſo an Ape, a Lion, &amp; a Serpent, ſo that he was in danger either to periſh by them, or together with them by famin. The poor man compaſſionates him, lets down the cord for him, but the Ape takes the advantage, and gets up by it; He puts again for the man, and his Lion aſcends: A third offer he makes, and up comes the Serpent: And laſtly, he draws up the man, who for the preſent is much taken with this courteſie, promiſes largely, earneſtly entreats the poore man, to let him ſee him at his houſe. The poor man, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118393:17"/>a reward, goes to his houſe the next day; but our rich man now would not ſee him, nor is he to be ſpoken with. The poor man returns, and muſt to the Wood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for his fuel; the Ape ſpies him, preſents him a burden of ſticks, ready broken and laid together; there was his thankfulneſs: The next day he goes, the Lion meets him, and preſents him ſome Camels laden, which he drives home, and unlading them, is enrich'd with much treaſure. He walks that way a third time, not now for necſſity, but recreation, where the Serpent creeps to him with a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtone in her mouth, which ſhe lets fall at her Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors feet. The Moral is onely this: That even the bruit creatures, are often more grateful, and mindful of a good turn, then man, their great Maſter is. O let it not be ſo! Know that unthankfulneſs, is not onely a paradoxe in manners, but a Prodigy in nature: be <hi>thankefull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Be <hi>frugal</hi> and <hi>thrifty, Prov.</hi> 21.20. <hi>There is treaſure to be deſired in the dwelling of the wiſe, but a fooliſh man ſpends it up.</hi> Squander not by looſe and luxurious cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, what God allows thee to gather, with ſo much pains and induſtry. It were well for many Husbandmen, if more Parſley were growing in their Gardens, if they were more parſimonious, and leſſe prodigal. If thou haſt a care to ſave what God ſends, thy family will be better provided for, and thou ſhalt be able with eaſe and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, to diſcharge all publique Taxes and Aſſeſsments. Abridge thy ſelf of ſuperfluities, and thou ſhalt not want neceſſaries. Our Engliſh Martyrology, hath a Relation of a woman, who being in priſon at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (where alſo the laſt bloud of Martyrs was ſhed in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time) when ſhe might have had better fare, confined her ſelf to a courſe and ſpare diet, as preparing her ſelf to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo, what neceſſity, and the cruelty of her enemies might bring her to ſuffer. Indeed it is good for all men to ſtraiten themſelves, whiles Gods hand is enlarged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118393:18"/>them; ſo ſhall they be better fitted to paſs through thoſe ſtraits, which Gods Providence, may bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Conſider, that it is better looking through a weak lattice window, then a ſtrong iron grate. Conſider, that thou ſoweſt thy Furrow by the handful, not by the ſack. Alas! how can they thrive, who eat or drink up their Crop, before they reap it. Be frugal while you have it; it will be too late to put two fingers into the purſe, when you have thrown all away by handfuls.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Be <hi>Charitable,</hi> liberally charitable: When I wiſh you to be thrifty, I would not have you ſordid and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; Grudge not your gleanings to the poore: I know the unconſcionable rapacity of ſome Gleaners: Be watchful, not waiward, careful, not niggardly. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6, 7, 8. <hi>He which ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly; and he which ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap bountifully;</hi> Let every man therefore, <hi>give not grudgingly, for God loveth a chearful giver; And God is able to make all grace abound towards you, that yee having all-ſufficiency in all things, may abound to every good work.</hi> This County hath been anciently famous for good houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping: At our Yeomans Table, you might have as good entertainment, as at the beſt Gentlemans, not for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of meſes, but for ſolid ſufficiency of meat, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty welcome. And it is ſaid, that when Hoſpitality died in <hi>England</hi> ſhe gave her laſt groan amongſt the Yeomen of <hi>Kent.</hi> I think I may ſpeak it without flattery, That even to this day, the doors and hands, the tables and kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins of Yeomen and Farmers, are as bountiful and hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitable, as beneficial to the poor, as many Gentlemens, who though they have great eſtates, have little heart to doe good, and the Travellers obſervation of <hi>Englands</hi> fault, <hi>Camini mali,</hi> that we had ill Clocks, and worſe Chimnies, may for one part of it, be verified in too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many Gentlemens houſes, for their Chimnies ſeldome ſmoak with charity.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118393:18"/>
            <p n="7">7. Be <hi>Religious:</hi> I propound this laſt, becauſe I would have it lie uppermoſt in your memories, and come firſt into your thoughts and practiſe. Be <hi>religious,</hi> I ſay, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſervant of God, and of Chriſtian duties: Moſt of your affairs have ſuch a peculiar dependance upon Gods Providence, that there lies the moſt ſpecial obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you of all ſecular callings) to ſeek to daily, and to ſerve God. Your neglects of God are ſtupendiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Neither ſay they in their heart, Let us now fear the Lord our God, that giveth rain, both the former and the latter in his ſeaſon; He reſorveth unto us the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed weeks of the Harveſt.</hi> Conſider farther, thy very buſineſs invites thee to holy contemplations. Moſt of the parables, ſimilitudes, arguments of the Prophets, Apoſtles, Chriſt, God himſelf uſed in Scripture, to teach and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade any Chriſtian duty, are taken from the field, or graſſe, or corn, or flowers, or ſeed, or rain, or cattel, &amp;c. or ſomewhat belonging to Husbandry: ſo that I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the words of <hi>Job,</hi> cap. 12.7, 8. <hi>Ask now the Beaſts, and they ſhall teach thee, or ſpeak to the Earth, and it ſhall ſhew thee thy duty.</hi> The labour, ſerviceableneſs, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of your cattel, preaches your duty of induſtry, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and ſerviceableneſs to God: The fruitfulneſs of your fields and folds, calls upon you for fruitfulneſs in your lives: The increaſe of your ſeed, for growth of grace; You cannot ſow and reap in a day; this teaches you that Leſſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. <hi>by patient continuance in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, to ſeek for glory, and honour, and immortality, you wait for the Harveſt:</hi> This teaches you to wait for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, at that general Judgement, the laſt and univerſal <hi>Harveſt of the Earth:</hi> as 'tis called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.15. To ſpeak of all that your Calling teaches you, would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage me to begin another Sermon, and it is now high time, that I make an end of this. I conclude; you ſee my beloved friends, that Husbandry it ſelf is the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmans
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118393:19"/>Sermon; and if I ſhould Preach to you but one Sermon in a yeare, yet your own buſineſs would preach a Sermon to you every day, of your particular duties; So that if you ſhould forget what I have ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you this day, I intreat you to obſerve, what your own imployments ſpeak daily unto you; Induſtry, Humility, Patience, Contentation, Thankfulneſs, Frugality, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Increaſe in Grace, and all Chriſtian vertues: So will God love you, if you thus love Husbandry; So ſhall I have cauſe to think, that I could not more pertinently conclude a Sermon unto Husbandmen, then by intimating unto you, That Husbandry is a Sermon; which both you and I muſt learn, practiſe, and live by; that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Honour of God, the Ornament, Advantage, and Eſtabliſhment, of our Callings and Country, of our Eſtates and Families, of our Bodies and Souls, We have loved Husbandry.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
